穿上一件破旧的长衫
Wearing a long-tattered gown,
径直来到鲁镇酒店
I went straight to the pub in Lu Town.
叫来伙计 温两碗酒
I called the waiter and ordered two bowls of wine
一碟茴香豆九文大钱
and a plate of fennel beans for 9 coins.
我说着之乎者也 惹来嘲笑
I spoke in a Classical Chinese style (obscure or complicated language to sound intelligent), which drew ridicule.
不知不觉涨红了脸
Unconsciously, my face turned red.
你怎么这样污我的清白
How can you tarnish my innocence like this?
喝口酒与他们继续争辩
I took a sip of wine and continued to argue with them.
骆驼祥子之所以死
The reason why Xiangzi (from Rickshaw Boy) died
是因为他拉车不够努力
was because he did not work hard enough to pull his rickshaw.
鲁迅的每一篇文章
In every article by Lu Xun,
都碰了不能碰的话题
he touches upon the untouchable topics.
陈胜吴广的日子不甜
Chen Sheng and Wu Guang did not have sweet lives (first uprising against the Qin dynasty)
是因为不能脚踏实地
because they did not have their feet on the ground (being realistic).
最后时刻目光移向我
At the last moment, everyone in the pub turned their eyes toward me,
问我到底算个什么东西
asking what kind of thing did I become.
我看看长衫说我是
I looked at my long gown and said that I was...
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
他那离谱的文笔 质问我服不服气
In his bizarre writing style, he questioned if I was convinced or not.
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
劳动力倒进河里 我也不便宜卖你
Even if my labor falls into the river, I won't sell myself cheaply to you.
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
你开着兰博基尼 却笑我不够努力
You drive a Lamborghini but laugh at me for not working hard enough.
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
这腐朽的旧社会 和我有寄吧关系
What does this decaying old society have to do with me?
虽然我每天都洗脸
Although I wash my face every day,
但口袋比脸还干净
my empty pockets are cleaner than my face.
我只好穿着长衫
I have to wear a changshan (traditional Manchu robe),
替官老爷抄书忙个不停
and work hard copying books for the officials.
本以为工作很清闲
I thought the job would be easy,
不曾想却是玖玖陆
but it turned out to be 996 (from 9:00 AM to 9:00 PM, 6 days per week).
干完后因恶意讨薪
After finishing my work, I maliciously demanded my wages,
饥饿的我被官兵抓走
and the hungry me was arrested by the officials.
这万恶的旧社会
Why does this extremely evil old society
为什么会没有劳动法
have no labor laws?
我们寻常百姓的尊严
Why is the dignity of us common people
为何会轻易被肉食者践踏
so easily trampled by the meat eaters?
这些离谱的故事与遭遇
These outrageous stories and experiences of suffering,
现在也没人敢回答
no one dares to answer them now.
最后食客们目光移向我
Finally, the diners turned their eyes toward me,
问我你为何一点也不怕
asking why was I not afraid at all.
我笑着说因为我是
I smiled and said because I am...
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
势单力薄的枝丫 早已放弃了挣扎
The small and weak branches have already given up struggling long ago.
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
棱角被岁月冲刷 徒留了几道伤疤
The edges and corners wore away over time, leaving only a few scars.
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
乐观是我的爪牙 面具下眼泛泪花
Optimism is my claws and teeth, while tears flow behind my mask.
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
你问我幸不幸福 我只想说句脏话
When you ask me if I am happy, I just want to curse.
听我说完了之后
After I finished speaking,
店内充满快活的空气
the air in the pub was filled with joy.
那些谩骂质疑反驳嘲笑
What do those insults, doubts, refutations, and ridicule
与我有何关系
have to do with me?
读书是为了中华崛起
Studying is for the rise of China,
而不是去送外卖快递
not for delivering takeout or packages.
所有人听完后露出放肆的笑容
After everyone listened, they all showed a candid smile,
除了那个傻逼的
except for that idiot...
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
撕开这腐朽的墙 寻一丝正道的光
Tear down this decaying wall, and seek the light of righteousness.
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
无论批评和赞扬 都需要有人鼓掌
Regardless of criticism or praise, there needs to be someone applauding.
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
精选的评论之上 有多少热血难凉
From all the top comments, how much hot blood is hard to cool down?
阳光开朗孔乙己 阳光开朗孔乙己
A sunny and cheerful Kong Yiji.
孔明是我的理想 商鞅是我的下场
Kong Ming (Zhuge Liang, most accomplished strategist during the Three Kingdoms period) is my ideal, yet Shang Yang (minister of Qin, executed for treason by dismemberment) is my fate.